"Do Vitamin D Supplements Help Prevent Diabetes, Cancer Mortality, and Overall Mortality?"
The VITAL study
was a randomized trial
to test whether
vitamin D supplementation
could prevent
cardiovascular disease
or cancer.
It also tested fish oil
and convincingly showed
that the use of omega-3s
is not effective
in preventing
cardiovascular disease,
but normal-weight
study participants
randomized to vitamin D
did end up
having a lower incidence
of cancer.
Over a period of five years,
a 24 percent lower risk
of getting cancer.
But overweight
or obese individuals did not.
The dose used in the study,
2,000 units a day,
may not have led
to similar results
in overweight
and obese participants
due to the higher
vitamin D requirements
of such individuals.
2,000 units a day may be enough
to get normal weight people
up to target,
but obese adults may need
at least
two to three times more,
a dose closer to 3,000
to 6,000 units a day
to reach the same blood levels.
A similar result was found
in the largest ever
vitamin D diabetes trial,
where pre-diabetics randomized
to take 4,000 units a day
reduced their risk of slipping
into full-blown diabetes
by 29 percent,
but it seemed to work
only if they were not obese.
That's why,
in the future perhaps,
vitamin D clinical trials
should be based on
achieved vitamin D
concentrations in the blood,
rather than
one-size-fits-all dosing.
For example, if you look at
vitamin D concentrations
achieved in
breast cancer trials,
regardless of which group
the subjects were randomized to,
there was a whopping
82 percent lower incidence rate
of breast cancer for women
with vitamin D concentrations
greater than or equal to
60 ng/ml
versus less than 20,
and the higher
their levels were,
the lower
their breast cancer risk
seemed to fall.
But if you just
lump everyone together,
it's no longer
a randomized controlled trial,
and we get back to the issue
of confounding,
like maybe the women
only had higher levels
of the sunshine vitamin
because they were outside
jogging every day,
and we know that
physical activity alone
may decrease breast cancer risk.
The finding of benefit
in certain subgroups
of study individuals,
like less cancer
among those
who are not overweight,
or less diabetes
for those who are not obese,
are examples
of secondary analyses,
where you go back
after the trial's over
to see whether
it may have worked
in some subset,
even if the intervention
had flopped overall.
This isn't uncommon,
but such results
must be interpreted cautiously,
because you can slice and dice
practically any data set
and come up with
some sort of spurious fluke
if you try hard enough.
But if you put all of
the randomized controlled trials
on vitamin D supplementation
for the prevention
of type 2 diabetes together,
daily supplementation with 1,000
or more units of vitamin D
does indeed reduce the risk
of diabetes among pre-diabetics.
In the 3 large trials
that were specifically designed
and conducted
for the prevention of diabetes,
vitamin D supplementation
reduced the risk
of developing diabetes
by about 10 percent overall.
What about putting all
the randomized controlled
vitamin D studies together
for cancer prevention?
Those randomized
to take vitamin D supplements
were 13 percent less likely
to die from cancer
over the subsequent
3 to 10 years.
Now vitamin D supplementation
wasn't able
to reduce the risk
of getting cancer,
but it was shown
to significantly reduce
the risk of dying from cancer.
I mean, it's a tiny benefit,
basically taking these people's
chances of dying from cancer
over a span of a few years
from around 24 in 1,000
to, like, 21 in 1,000,
but it's a beneficial effect
on lowering cancer mortality
nonetheless,
based on
a comprehensive analysis
of 10 randomized
controlled trials
involving more than
80,000 participants.
Note that a 13 percent reduction
in cancer mortality
doesn't necessarily mean
you live any longer.
Since vitamin D supplements
don't help heart disease,
killer number one,
you would only expect
your lifespan
to significantly benefit
if your heart disease risk
is really low.
Only if you're protected
from heart disease
would killer number two
take on a more prominent role,
or if there was
some other reason
you were at
particularly high cancer risk.
For those getting
inadequate sunshine,
I recommend
2,000 international units
a day of vitamin D3.
Daily dosing is important
since taking monthly
or yearly mega-doses
doesn't seem to work
for reducing cancer mortality.
And D3 may be preferable.
Historically,
it's been suggested
there's no difference
in terms of effectiveness
between the two types
you can buy,
vitamins D2 and D3,
but it turns out that vitamin D3
may work better,
as it can increase D levels
by about 75 percent,
compared to the same dose of D2,
only increasing levels
by about a third.
So it looks like D3
is about twice as effective
at raising blood levels.
Does it matter if you get
powder-filled capsules,
oil-based preparations,
or water-based preparations
of vitamin D?
Nope, they all appear
to raise your D levels the same.